Hey, what's up guys? My name is The
Cherno. Welcome back to my C++ series.
Today, we're going to be taking a look
at loops. So, when I say loops, I'm
specifically talking about for loops and
while loops. To put it into simple
terms, loops are basically things that
we can write in our code when we want to
perform certain operations multiple
times. So, a really simple example is
what if we wanted to print Hello World
five times, right? Would we just copy
and paste that line of code five times
or maybe put that code into a function
and then call that function five times,
like literally five times in our code?
Should we do it that way? Or can we just
use a loop to say, "Hey, I want this
code here to run five times in a row."
Loops are also important kind of for big
picture stuff. So, picture a game,
right? If you've written a game, odds
are you want to keep the game running,
right? You don't want to just like run
the game and render one frame and exit
and that's it, right? Game done, like
one frame, I rendered my frame, I'm
going to exit, I'm done now. That would
be very weird. You want to keep the game
actually playing. And so, for that, what
you need is something called a game
loop. And a game loop is just something
that essentially says, "Hey,
like while the game is running, so while
the user hasn't decided to quit the
game, keep updating the game, keep
rendering the game, keep moving all the
characters around, keep doing
everything, like over and over again,
frame by frame." So, loops are very
important for programming. They're used
in like every program, right? It's the
same thing as like conditionals, which
we talked about last week, video up
here.
That kind of stuff, right? This is much
like that. Like you need to know this
stuff really well because you're going
to be using it as one of your primary
tools when you actually write code, when
you write a program. So, first of all,
let's start with for loops. The example
that I gave earlier was printing Hello
World five times. And again, we could
achieve that just by copying and pasting
this log call five times. And if I run
this code, you're going to see that we,
of course, do get Hello World printed to
the console five times. However, to make
our lives a little bit easier, what we
can do is write a for loop. For loops
start with the keyword for and then
basically break up into three parts.
Each of these three parts are separated
by a semicolon. The first part is a
variable declaration. So, usually you
would declare some sort of variable
here. So, we're going to write int i =
0. Now, the variable name being i is a
little bit of a convention. Some say it
stands for iterator, which of course is
relevant here because we'll be iterating
over this code. You can really call this
variable absolutely anything. It also
doesn't have to be an integer and it
also doesn't have to be equal to zero.
After I show you guys a simple for loop,
we are going to break it down a little
bit and see what we can do because for
loops are actually really, really
flexible and you can really like make
them do pretty much anything you want.
The second part is a condition.
Basically, this says that as long as
this condition is true, I'm going to
keep executing code inside the for loop.
So, in this case, since we want this
code to execute five times, right? This
log hello world, we want to call that
five times, we're going to write i is
less than five and I'll explain how this
ties in together in just a second. The
last statement is basically code that
will be called before the next iteration
of the for loop. So, in this case, what
we want to do is write i ++, which
basically is the same thing as saying i
+ = 1 or i = i + 1, which basically
means that we're going to increment our
i variable, which starts at zero of
course here. We're going to increment it
by one, we're going to plus one it every
single iteration of this for loop. And
then of course, we provide a body, which
is basically just saying that anything
in this body is the contents of our for
loop. So, this is actually what's going
to be looped. This is the code that will
be executed multiple times. I say
multiple times, but of course, these
conditions are going to determine
whether this code is executed at all or
maybe once or it could be a hundred
times, right? It's all depending on this
condition. So, let's go ahead and stick
one of our log calls into here
and I'll get rid of all of these extra
ones. If we hit our five to run our
code, you'll see we get the same result,
five times hello world. Okay, cool. So,
let's break this down a little bit. This
declaration is the first thing that will
happen. When our instruction pointer
reaches this line of code here, it will
first of all declare whatever is written
in here, right? So, in this case, we're
creating a new variable called I. What
it will then do is immediately check to
see if this condition is true. If this
condition is true, we're going to go
ahead and jump to the body of our for
loop and execute whatever is there. When
we have finished executing the body and
we hit this curly bracket here, this
closing one, we're going to go back up
to here and perform whatever code is
written here. So, in this case, we're
incrementing I by one. After that
happens, we're going to go back to the
condition and check to see if the
condition is true. Now, of course, at
this point, I used to be zero, now we've
incremented it by one, so now we're
checking if one is less than five. It
is, of course, less than five, so we're
going to jump back here and perform this
code. This is going to keep going until
finally I will be equal to four, we're
going to run this code, jump up here,
increment I by one, which gives us five,
and now we're comparing if five is less
than five. However, five is not less
than five because five is equal to five.
So, this condition is false, which means
we now jump to line 10 over here to
execute cin.get. And that, in essence,
is how that for loop will actually run
five times. Now, I just want to stress
that these three parts of this for loop
declaration are exactly what I said they
are, right? This is just code that will
be executed at the beginning of the for
loop once only. This is a comparison or
some some kind of boolean that will be
evaluated before the next iteration of
the for loop. And then this is some kind
of dec- like it's some kind of code that
will be executed at the end of our for
loop. So, what I could do is like
literally I could say actually in I
equals zero, I'm going to put that over
here and leave this completely blank,
just like that, right? That's perfectly
valid code. I could also say that this I
plus plus, I'm actually just going to
drop it here, right? Cuz it's that's
going to have the same result. And if I
run this, even though it looks a little
bit weird, we're actually going to get
the exact same result because we haven't
actually changed the behavior of this
code at all. We've just moved some
things around. Similarly, I could write
a Boolean here called like condition or
something, set it equal to true, and
have that to be my actual condition,
right? So, I've got my condition. I'm
going to do I plus plus, and then I
might do something like if I
is not less than five anymore, right?
I'm going to set condition equal to
false. And if I run this code, you can
see that I'm still going to get hello
world printed five times, because again,
I haven't changed the behavior of my
program. I've just rewritten the code in
a slightly different way. But I'm
telling you all this so that you know
that for loops, they can do anything,
right? Like you don't have to always be
like for in I equals zero, I is less
than five, I plus plus. That's boring,
right? They can contain any kind of
statements you want. You could also, of
course, call functions in that like for
loop statement. Anything, right? The
possibilities are literally endless. You
could also get rid of the condition
entirely, which basically means that
it's the same thing as writing true,
right? This will never be false. And if
I run this, it's actually going to be an
endless loop, right? It's never going to
end. So, if I hit F5 right now to run
this, you'll see that we're going to
actually keep printing hello world as
our program keeps running until we
manually terminate it. So, that's pretty
much it for for loops. I mean, they're
really, really simple for doing like for
for running code multiple times. So, for
example, I want to print hello world
five times. Fantastic for that. Really
easy to set up for that. Also, they're
really useful with arrays when you want
to kind of go through an array kind of
linearly like that as well. Very useful
for that. Um the next thing that we'll
move on to is while loops. So, a while
loop is much like a for loop. It's just
that it doesn't have this kind of
statement at the beginning and this
statement at the end. It's just got a
condition. So, basically, to write a
while loop, we'll write the keyword
while, and then inside here, we put some
kind of condition. So, for example, I is
less than five, right? As an example.
And of course, I was declared up here.
So, if we run this, this will basically
perform whatever code is in here as long
as I is less than five. So, if we were
to rewrite our for loop, let me just
bring back the for loop to what it was
originally.
If we If we wanted to basically
replicate this for loop in here, we
would have to write int I equals zero
out here and then do the I plus plus at
the end of the loop. So, over here,
right? And then right now what we have
here is actually exactly the same. I'm
just going to in between these, I'm just
going to print like a whole bunch of
equal signs just to separate the two
statements, but if I run this, you can
see that we get the same result from
both loops, right? They're both printing
hello world five times. So, why use a
while loop instead of a for loop or like
when would you use a for loop instead of
a while loop? Basically, it comes down
to whether or not you need a variable,
right? Because these loops are
identical. You can use them
interchangeably, right? It's more a
matter of convention or a matter of
style than it is an actual hard rule
because again, like there's no actual
difference between the two loops. They
can do exactly the same thing. Uh if if
you so want want them to, but the
conventions are basically if you have a
certain condition that already exists
that you want to just kind of compare.
So, for example, I mentioned that whole
game loop example where you had a
variable called running and you might
want to kind of keep that game loop
going as long as that running variable
is true because running equals true
basically means that your program is
still running. If you wanted to do
something like that, I would probably
use a while loop because all we need is
a condition. We don't need to be
changing the condition after every
iteration. We don't need to declare the
condition to start off the loop. It's
already a variable that we've got or a
function call that we can use and that's
just going to be completely like fine,
right? It's not something that we
actually have to keep kind of updating
or set up initially, none of that stuff,
right? Whereas if I wanted to go through
an array and the array had a certain
size, for example, my array was 10
elements long, then I would use a for
loop because first of all, I want to run
that code exactly 10 times, so I want to
keep track of some kind of variable and
only run that loop 10 times, but also
that variable will be useful for
accessing elements inside that array
because if I want to access every
element in a 10 element array, I need
some kind of offset so that I can like
an index so that I can access an element
in that array. And of course we're going
to talk about arrays in the future, but
that I variable that we happen to be
tracking and it's going to go 0 1 2 3 4
5 as our iterations go on is going to be
absolutely perfect for that. So we've
got four and we've got while, but there
is actually one more loop that we have
and it's called do-while loop. Now these
aren't that useful. I don't personally
use these that often, but they are there
and they do have some uses. Although
again, you won't be seeing these
anywhere near as much as for loops or
while loops. So basically we write the
do keyword and then we have a body and
then at the end we write while and we
have some kind of condition. So for
example, again, I'll just do I is less
than five. The only difference between a
do-while loop and a while loop is that
this body will be executed at least once
no matter what, right? So for example,
if we if we change this into I situation
so that instead we actually just have a
condition
and it might be equal to false.
If I stick that condition in here, this
while is actually going to function much
like an if statement in the sense that
if this is false, well then it's never
going to run the code in here. However,
a do-while loop, even if this is false,
right? If it is set to condition,
condition is false, it will function as
if it's not a loop. It's going to run
the code here once. It's going to come
down to the while, look at the
condition. Ah, the condition's false, so
I'm not going to loop. And that's pretty
much it. That's how do-while loops work.
All right. So that's pretty much it for
today's video. Hope you guys enjoyed
very basic introduction to loops. We're
going to be using these a lot throughout
the series. They're used in like pretty
much every algorithm you can think of.
Loops are extremely useful. When we talk
about arrays, we'll be talking about how
we can use for loops to access arrays
and all of that stuff. So everything
will tie in nicely. I'm going to do a
more in-depth look at them sometime in
the future where we're actually going to
look at the disassembly and look at the
actual CPU instructions that get
generated for loops and take a bit of a
deeper look. I just didn't want to make
this video too complicated, so the link
to that in-depth video will be somewhere
in the description when that video
actually comes out. But, I hope you guys
enjoyed this video. If you did, please
hit that like button. You can follow me
on Twitter and Instagram. And, if you
really like this series and you want to
see more episodes and you want to
support this series, you can support me
on patreon.com/thecherneau.
And, I will see you next time. Goodbye.